{"tossups": [{"question": "This location is the setting of an \u201cOutdoor Scene\u201d often paired with \u201cThe Pond\u201d and \u201cHalloween\u201dby Charles Ives. One section of this region was dedicated on October 9, 1985, is a short walk from the Dakota apartment complex, and features a tile mosaic around the word \u201cImagine.\u201d A 1981 benefit concert to revive this location brought 500,000 people to it to listen to \u201cMrs. Robinson\u201d and other Simon and Garfunkel songs. The Strawberry Fields memorial to John Lennon is located in, for ten points, what landmark green space designed by Frederick Law Olmstead in Manhattan?", "answer": "<b> Central Park</b> (accept<b> Central Park in the Dark</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s step-grandfather, White Man Runs Him, served as a scout for Custer\u2019s forces prior to the Battle of the Little Bighorn. This man published a book on buffalo jump techniques and, while serving in World War II, managed to steal 50 horses belonging to the SS, an exploit that helped this 2009 recipient of the Presidential Medal of Freedom become a War Chief. For ten points, name this Plains Indians War Chief of the Crow nation who died in 2016 at the age of 102.", "answer": "Joseph<b> Medicine Crow</b> High Bird", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man \u201cplaced his dithyrambs in the hands of the poet of Isoline\u201d in a letter signed \u201cDionysus;\u201dthat letter is one of his Wahnzettel [vahn-zettel], or Madness Letters. According to legend, after this man witnessed a horse being flogged in Turin, he ran to protect it and collapsed at its side. After this man\u2019s death, his sister Elizabeth compiled and published the unfinished<em> The Will to Power</em>, which describes the problem of nihilism, a philosophy that this thinker\u2019s earlier works explained was the end result of the death of God. For ten points, name this German philosopher who wrote<em> The Gay Science</em>.", "answer": "Friedrich<b> Nietzsche</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "One of this man\u2019s works ends with a prayer asking whether this is the \u201cfullness of Joy\u201d that the Lord promises. That work by this man opens with an \u201cexhortation of the mind to the contemplation of God,\u201dwho this man defined as a \u201cbeing greater than which none can be conceived\u201d in what is now considered the original ontological argument for God\u2019s existence. The<em> Proslogion</em> was written by, for ten points, what early 12th century Archbishop of Canterbury who is often considered the founder of Scholasticism?", "answer": "Saint<b> Anselm</b> of Canterbury Page 1", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "Jean-Jacque Maimoni was killed by friendly fire in this event. In carrying out this event, Wilfred Bose protested that he was not a Nazi. During this event, Dora Bloch was allowed to leave due to illness, then was killed anyway. Jonathan Netanyahu was the IDF\u2019s only fatality in this event; others killed included two members of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, who had hijacked Air France Flight 139. For ten points, name this July 4, 1976 counter-terrorism operation in which over 100 hostages were rescued from an airport in Uganda.", "answer": "<b> Entebbe</b> raid (accept Operation<b> Entebbe</b> or Operation<b> Thunderbolt</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A building in this city designed by Pierre Cardin has been derided for looking like an \u201cilluminated mushroom.\u201d This city is home to the Palace of Light and the Palazzo Dario, which was painted by Claude Monet. To protect trade secrets, this city forbade glassmakers on its island of Murano from leaving. Canaletto depicted this city in his painting<em> Return of Bucentaure, Ascension Day</em> and his many depictions of its<em> Canalasso</em>. For ten points, name this Italian city built precariously on the Mediterranean, where gondolas navigate its many canals.", "answer": "<b> Venice</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Juan de Betanzos wrote a narrative history of this conflict. The Canari people switched sides during this conflict, choosing to follow the loser of this war. The decisive battle in this conflict was the Battle of Quipaipan. The loyal generals Ruminahui and Quizquiz supported the eventual winner of this conflict, who was captured at the Battle of Cajamarca shortly after this war ended. For ten points, name this war fought over a throne left vacant by the death of Huayna Capac, which ended when Huascar defeated was by his half-brother Atahualpa.", "answer": "<b> Incan Civil</b> War (accept War of the<b> Incan Succession</b>; accept War of the<b> Two Brothers</b>; prompt on war between Huascar and Atahualpa before Huascar is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man scored a decisive victory against the Macromanni after forming a pincer with Gaius Saturninus. His invasion of Armenia allowed for the return of the Roman standards lost at Carrhae. This man was forced to divorce Vipsania and marry Julia the Elder; Tacitus notes that his hatred of his wife may have led him to retire to Rhodes. He met his end in Capri when he was smothered by the prefect Macro, to be succeeded by a man whom this emperor described as a \u201cviper in Rome\u2019s bosom.\u201d For ten points, name this son of Livia Drusilla who was succeeded as Roman emperor by Caligula.", "answer": "<b> Tiberius</b> Claudius Nero (do not accept or prompt on Claudius or Nero alone)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This complex houses the \u201cthrone of the immortal one,\u201d or Akal Takht. Massa Ranghar profaned this structure by performing acts of gluttony and debauchery in it. Reginald Dyer commanded troops that committed a massacre near this structure in the Jallianwalla Bagh garden. This structure is located in a lake whose waters are known as the \u201cpool of ambrosial nectar.\u201d In 1984, two bodyguards disgruntled over the fact that this complex was targeted in Operation Blue Star assassinated Indira Gandhi. For ten points, name this<em> gurdwara</em> in Amritsar, the holiest site in Sikhism.", "answer": "<b> Golden Temple</b> of Amritsar (or<b> Harmandir Sahib</b>; accept<b> Darbar Sahib</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "These three countries fought each other on opposite sides during the Crimean War. For ten points, name these three members of the Triple Entente in WWI.", "answer": "<b> United Kingdom</b>,<b> France</b>, and<b> Russia</b> (accept Great<b> Britain</b> or<b> England</b> for UK)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was defeated by his brother at Poenari Castle. Prince Basarab the Elder fled before this man, who was supported by the soldiers of Stephen Bathory. After sparking a conflict by refusing to pay the jizya, this man mistakenly targeted the tent of Ishak Pasha during his \u201cNight Attack.\u201d This member of the Order of the Dragon was opposed by his brother, Radu the Handsome, while attempting to defend his vovoideship from Ottoman invasion. For ten points, name this Wallachian ruler known for his method of disposing of foes on wooden stakes.", "answer": "<b> Vlad the Impaler</b> (or<b> Vlad III</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The British sponsored a failed scheme to plant vast amounts of peanuts in this modern-day country to provide much-needed oil. A rebellion in this modern-day country that was</b> <b>crushed by Gustav Adolf von Gotzen was led by Kinjikitile (+)</b> <b>Ngwale, who spread the</b> <b>belief that bullets would turn into water if warriors consumed a \u201cwar medicine\u201d called</b><em><b> maji</b></em><b>. A colony encompassing the territory of this modern-day country was the target of the Allies in the (*) </b> East Africa Campaign, which managed to wrest it from German colonial control. For ten points, name this modern-day country whose territory was mostly comprised of the colony of Tanganyika.", "answer": "<b> Tanzania</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This composer\u2019s namesake approach to music education made heavy use of xylophones. He falsely claimed to be a co-founder of the White Rose resistance movement during de-Nazification, but he did accept a Nazi commission to replace (+) Mendelssohn\u2019s work on </b><em><b>A Midsummer Night\u2019s Dream</b></em><b>. He included \u201cBlanzifor et Helena\u201d in a cantata, the first part of</b><em><b> Trionfi</b></em><b>, whose texts were taken from a collection of medieval (*) </b> secular songs and which opens and closes with an ode to the title \u201cwhirling wheel\u201d of fate. For ten points, name this composer, who wrote \u201cO Fortuna\u201d as part of his<em> Carmina Burana</em>.", "answer": "Carl<b> Orff</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>At one battle at this site, duckboards were required on ground level and soldiers drowned in mud if they lost their balance; during that battle, one side took Menin Road and Polygon Wood. An attempt to capture this city during the (+) Spring Offensive led Alexander Haig to issue the \u201cBacks to the Wall\u201d order. A corruption of this city\u2019s name named a popular satirical trench newspaper that was popular among troops fighting in this city\u2019s (*)</b> salient. For ten points, name this Flemish town that was the site of several bloody battles, including the first major use of poison gas, during World War I.", "answer": "<b> Ypres</b> [eep-rah] (or<b> Ieper</b>; or<b> Wipers</b>; accept<b> Passchendaele</b> before \u201cSpring\u201d is read) Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Early in this work, one figure answers why \u201cdevil\u201d and \u201csnake\u201d are used interchangeably in stories of the Garden of Eden.</b><em><b> 60 Minutes\u2019</b></em><b> Mike Wallace co-produced this work with Louis Lomax. In this work, an excerpt of a play called</b><em><b> The Trial</b></em><b> is shown in which the</b> <b>declaration \u201cI charge the (+)</b> <b>white man with being the greatest murderer on earth!\u201d is</b> <b>given by Louis Farrakhan. Malcolm X rose in prominence after his interviews in this work were (*)</b> broadcast. For ten points, name this July 1959 five-part documentary about \u201cthe rise of Black Racism,\u201d focusing on the Nation of Islam\u2019s \u201cgospel of hate.\u201d", "answer": "The<b> Hate that Hate Produced</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>Shortly after the first of these events, Nelli Kim matched the feat three times. According to legend, Omega\u2019s anticipation of this event was ignored by officials, who claimed that</b> <b>equipment with three (+)</b> <b>digits would be suitable for use. Eight years after this event,</b> <b>digits would be suitable for use. Eight years after this event,</b> <b>Mary Lou Retton matched it under the tutelage of the same coach, Bela (*)</b> <b>Mary Lou Retton matched it under the tutelage of the same coach, Bela (*)</b> Karolyi. This event took place seven times at Montreal, beginning with the uneven bars. For ten points, name this flawless feat performed at the 1976 Summer Olympics by a certain Romanian gymnast.", "answer": "Nadia<b> Comaneci\u2019s</b> [koh-mah-nesh\u2019s] perfect<b> 10</b>s (accept descriptions; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>These weapons were used in coordination with</b><em><b> panokseon</b></em><b> to win the Battles of Okpo and Myeongnyang for Yi Sun-Shin. Lennart Torstenson commanded these weapons</b> <b>effectively to thwart Count Tilly\u2019s advance at (+)</b> <b>Breitenfeld, and early heavy-usage of</b> <b>these these weapons doomed John Talbot at Castillon. Variants of these weapons included serpentines and culverins, and Orban introduced them to (*)</b> Mehmed II, allowing the capture of Constantinople. For ten points, name these weapons mounted on galleons and frigates, large guns that shot heavy stone and metal balls.", "answer": "<b> cannon</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Marco Sanudo ruled this island after it was conquered by the French during the Fourth Crusade. An early Bronze Age settlement on this island was at Phylakopi. People from this</b> <b>island are told \u201cThe strong (+)</b> <b>do as they can, and the weak suffer what they must\u201d in</b> <b>response to their refusal to submit to rule; shortly after, this island\u2019s males are killed and the women and children sold into slavery by the Athenians. A famous artifact from this island was called \u201ca big (*) </b> gendarme\u201d by Renoir, and is believed to be by Alexandros of Antioch. For ten points, name this Greek island whose \u201cdialogue\u201d with Athens is recorded in Thucydides\u2019<em> History</em> <em>of the Peloponnesian War</em>, the discovery site of an armless statue of Venus.", "answer": "<b> Melos</b> (accept<b> Milo</b>; accept Venus de<b> Milo</b>; accept<b> Melian</b> dialogue) Page 11", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>One theory of the cause of this event was supported by a Antonio Camargo and Glen Penfield discovery. Luis Alvarez proposed one cause of this event, declaring that chondrites</b> <b>probably deposited the staggering level of (+)</b> <b>iridium he found in shocked quartz in the</b> <b>crust. A decade later, the discovery of the (*)</b> Chicxulub [chick-shu-loob] crater bolstered that theory of this event. For ten points, name this devastating event that marks the boundary between two eras of geologic time and occurred roughly 66 million years ago.", "answer": "<b> Cretaceous-Tertiary</b> (or<b> Cretaceous-Paleogene</b>)<b> extinction</b> event (accept<b> K-T</b> or<b> K-Pg extinction</b> event; accept descriptions of \u201cthe<b> end of the dinosaurs</b>\u201d)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {"question": "<b>One man took advantage of the high prevalence of handkerchiefs in this event, which made a rule about \u201copen hands\u201d unenforceable. James Parker unsuccessfully tried to stop this event, whose perpetrator said \u201cI have (+) done my duty\u201d before being knocked out by rifle butts. After being inspired by Gaetano Bresci, one participant in this event managed to hide a (*)</b> gun under a bandage wrap. For ten points, name this 1901 event that took place at Buffalo\u2019s Pan-American Exposition and resulted in Leon Czolgosz [zhul-gosh] being arrested for murder.", "answer": "<b> assassination of</b> William<b> McKinley</b> ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One commander at this battle allegedly strove to copy the Ottomans at Nicopolis in the manner he defended his flanks. This battle was preceded by the siege of Harfleur</b> <b>and resulted in the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Troyes. One side in this battle defended its flanks</b> <b>with wooden stakes, though these could not prevent a raid on that side\u2019s baggage train. In a play, the Band of (*)</b> Brothers speech is given by Henry V before this battle, in which one side\u2019s charge was hampered by muddy ground. Like Crecy, this battle reaffirmed the superiority of the longbow. For ten points, name this English victory on St. Crispin\u2019s Day in the 100 Years War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Agincourt</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}